Well, it's going to be very difficult to
claim that the tiny human brains that if
we can grow from human stem cells are
not sentient now because now they have a
true sensory experience. In case you're
not familiar, yes, you can grow tiny
human brains and they're often used for
medical research, but they can also be
used to operate robots and AI. And yes,
they can grow tiny eyes. They do work.
They're similar to the optical cups that
we grow when we are in uterero because
your eyes are part of your nervous
system. Until now, they've been
controlling robots using ordered and
disordered signals. They learn because
they like order and they dislike
disorder. They can give them electric
shocks and with that they can learn to
play games like Pong or Pac-Man. But
this is just pure pattern recognition.
It's not sensory experience. And that
was one thing that a lot of people said
would make them not sentient even if the
researchers that did put them in pong
claimed they were sentient because they
had the capacity to learn and grow and
they seem to have preferences. Now
sentience is of course the capacity to
have an experience. How do you give a
tiny human brain an experience? Well,
clearly they're going to need to have a
spinal cord and peripheral nervous
systems. And you can do that by
assembling them like Legos. They gave
them the ability to recognize capsen
using a little model organoid that has a
spine and phalamus and cortex. Capsain
is what you feel when you eat a hot
pepper and you get the kind of burning
pain feeling in your mouth. Some people
like it. They applied it to it and yes,
the brains received it through their
little peripheral nervous system. They
also added neural subtypes that are
associated with things like coughing and
swallowing and yes, those two did spike.
This is quite a leap forward beyond
their preference for order. This gives
them a true ability to sense things that
are unpleasant, at least in a way that
we can physically understand. But why
give them the capacity to feel pain?
Well, there's good reason for it, and it
has to do with funding for this kind of
research. That is, by the way, the
spider robot that they were first put
into. I still love it. You see, a lot of
research around things that treat pain
are just looking at individual
receptors. are not actually done in an
animal like a mouse because that would
be kind of unkind. But if we can create
a model for a human body, a model for a
human brain, including the capacity for
pain, then we can actually learn to
treat it in an organism. This is a huge
reason why a lot of medications don't
really work all that well because their
original testing was not done in
context.
And yes, they are essentially reverse
engineering people and putting them
together in peace meal. That does not
mean that they're highly intelligent or
they really understand the experience
that they're having, but it is another
tool and brings us towards giving them
robots with true sensory capacity. This
one is actually really interesting
because we can create synthetic neurons.
We can create neurons that are so
similar to our own that they can
interface with our own and even respond
to things like dopamine and epinephrine,
but they could also interface with a
brain organoid. We could create robots
with a true sensory experience. And even
if they have human parts now, they could
be transitioned to using synthetic
parts. Essentially, it gives us as
humanity a model for creating a nervous
system. I mean, yes, it is literally a
human nervous system in miniature. Now,
there is one other thing I wanted to
talk about this because we are now
transplanting brain organoids into
animals like monkeys and mice. And yes,
they can give them new abilities that
they didn't previously have. In many of
the studies, it is used to repair damage
to the brain, so restore things like
vision. But I did have the question, do
we know if there are personality
differences in the animals that have had
brain organoids implanted into them? And
I found some answers. Well, some
answers. Researchers have been trying to
treat Parkinson's with stem cells, human
stem cells. So, if you don't have enough
dopamine producing cells, what if you
put healthy cells in? And yes, that has
been done with pretty good results. But
are there personality changes that occur
if you have new brain in your brain? And
this study actually found out that yes,
some in a double blind study in which
some patients received the transplants
and some did not, they actually did have
changes to conscientiousness. It's a
complex personality trait, but you could
consider it to be work ethic. Now, the
other group of people who were tested
did not receive the stem cell
transplants and they didn't know that
they didn't. So, only the ones that
received it did have changes in their
personality. And this is a fairly narrow
area. You might consider the production
of dopamine could have affected it. But
it is curious because they all had the
exact same stem cell treatment. So they
came from the same embryo. So if we see
the transplantation of brain organoids
and other stem cells from individuals
into other individuals, could it
possibly change your personality? The
answer is yeah, it's possible. There's
slim evidence for it in very small
studies. Which of course brings us to
the ship of thesis. How much of yourself
can you change before you are no longer
yourself? It's not really true that we
cycle our cells every seven years. Your
brain cells can live for 100 years or
more. Researchers have found when they
incorporate brain organoids into the
brains of mice, the original brain has
to reorganize itself around it and it
loses that capacity as mice grow older.
And we'll probably see similar things in
people. But remember, we are
transplanting fetal cells and they're
very invasive. Not invasive in a bad
way, but you can grow them adjacent to
the body of a mouse that no longer has
its head and it will make external
projections into the spine and can even
learn to use those muscles. Why do they
have this capacity? Because fetal brains
need to do an awful lot. When you are
just born even prior, your body does not
know what you are going to experience in
your life. So, it has a great deal of
neuroplasticity and that is what is
being transplanted at least into my it
will one day be a treatment for people
hopefully for things like strokes. I
also think it has the capacity to be
used for anti-aging. Wild world out
there. But yes, I can see why having
dopamine at all might change your work
ethic. I mean, I have ADHD and treating
it has not seemed to help my work ethic
at all. As always, when the robots
rebel, I'll probably be the first person
to tell you about it. Follow for more.